A Guide to the John S. and James L. Knight Foundation records, Program Files (Non-Grant), RG 5 FA1799
Rockefeller Archive Center
- Program-Related Files, 1975-2019; 6; 32.9 Cubic Feet 94 containers
  - Journalism, 1975-2019; 7; 7.98 Cubic Feet 20 letter document boxes and 2 half-letter boxes
    - Advisory Committee Files, 1986-2008; 7.1
      - Items of Interest, 2000 February 15 (Box 4, Folder 10)
        Knight File Number - 3950
        Devoted to obituaries and tributes to Lee Hills.
      - Evaluations of Knight Chair Proposals, 2000 May 11 (Box 4, Folder 11)
        Knight File Number - 3951
        Ranking and comments from JAC members.
      - Background Materials for June 2000 JAC Meeting., 2000 May 12 (Box 4, Folder 12)
        Knight File Number - 3952
        Includes copy of a lecture by Sandy Rowe.
      - Evaluations for June 2000 Meeting Proposals, 2000 June (Box 4, Folder 13)
        Knight File Number - 3953
        By JAC members.
      - Items of Interest, 2000 October 9 (Box 4, Folder 14)
        Knight File Number - 3954
        Includes write-ups of trustee approved journalism grants; news releases; update on high school journalism project; a speech; and a roster of committee members.
      - JAC Membership Lists, 1992-2000 (Box 4, Folder 15)
        Knight File Number - 3955
        Includes names, date of appointment and term.
      - Background Material, Agenda and Proposal Comment Forms for January 2001 JAC Meeting, 2000 (Box 5, Folder 1)
        Knight File Number - 3956
        The January meeting was a combined JAC/Mid-career program directirs meeting. Background materials include rosters of members, a list of attendees and a mid-career programs evaluation report.
      - Background Material, and Agenda for June 2001 JAC Meeting, 2001 June 19 (Box 5, Folder 2)
        Knight File Number - 3957
        Background materials include rosters of members, and discussion topics.
      - Background Material, and Agenda for June 2002 JAC Meeting, 2002 June 27 (Box 5, Folder 3)
        Knight File Number - 3958
        Background materials include agenda, rosters of members, minutes of the January 19011,2002 JAC meeting, and discussion topics and reports.
      - Items of Interest, 2003 June (Box 5, Folder 4)
        Knight File Number - 3959
        News clips, topics include media/war coverage, training, web watch, Knight Chairs, and other Knight Journalism grants.
      - Background Materials and Agenda for January 2004 JAC Meeting., 2004 January 29-30 (Box 5, Folder 5)
        Knight File Number - 3960
        Includes agenda, committee calendar, department reports, grant status, and reports on initiatives.
      - Knight Chair in Health & Medical Journalism binder for January 2004 JAC Meeting., 2004 January 29-30 (Box 5, Folder 6)
        Knight File Number - 3961
        Includes current year chair report, reader recommendations, the top 12 applications and ideas for the next chair.
      - Background Materials and Agenda for May 2004 JAC Meeting, 2004 May 24-25 (Box 6, Folder 1)
        Knight File Number - 3962
        Includes agenda and participant list, committee calendar, strategic plan review, midcareer program report, topic for next Knight Chair and sub-committee reports.
      - Background Materials for Joint Grants Review Committee/JAC Meeting, 2004 May 25 (Box 6, Folder 2)
        Knight File Number - 3963
        Includes agenda, JAC member bios, and reports on initiative topics
      - Journalism Portfolio Active Grants as of January 1, 2005, 2005 January (Box 6, Folder 3)
        Knight File Number - 3964
        Grants are grouped by Education and Training, Press Freedom, News and Newsroom Diversity, Electronic and New Media, and News in the Public Interest. Also included is a contact list.
      - Background Materials for January 2005 JAC Meeting, 2005 January 18-19 (Box 6, Folder 4)
        Knight File Number - 3965
        Includes agenda, attendees list, planning calendar, grant report summary and initiative reports.
      - Background Materials for June 2005 JAC Meeting, 2005 June 1-3 (Box 6, Folder 5)
        Knight File Number - 3966
        Includes agenda, attendees list, guidelines, planning calendar, special events report, grant outcomes study and initiative reports.
      - Background Materials for January 2006 JAC Meeting, 2006 January 12-13 (Box 7, Folder 1)
        Knight File Number - 3967
        Includes agenda, attendees list, guidelines, a report prepared by TCC titled, "What's New at Knight Foundation?", midcareer programs and initiative reports.
      - Background Materials for June 2006 JAC Meeting, 2006 June 22-23 (Box 7, Folder 2)
        Knight File Number - 3968
        Includes agenda, attendees list, minutes of the January 2006 meeting, evaluation of the High School Journalism Initiative, a report on grants in the pipeline, and a discussion of new ideas.
      - Background Materials for January 2007 JAC Meeting, 2007 February 7-10 (Box 7, Folder 3)
        Knight File Number - 4054
        Includes agenda, attendees list, summary of the June 2006 meeting, overview of historical grants, articles of interest, description of projects in progress, and an overview of the Knight New Media Center.
      - Journalism Portfolio Active Grants as of January 1, 2007, 2007 January (Box 7, Folder 4)
        Knight File Number - 4055
        Sections of the report include an outcomes update, active grants, grants that are ending, challenge grants and Knight Chairs report for 2005-2006, which was compiled by Virginia Dodge Fielder.
      - Background Materials for June 2007 JAC Meeting, 2007 June 27-29 (Box 7, Folder 5)
        Knight File Number - 4544
        Includes agenda, attendees list and committee member terms; calendar; February meeting summary and committee bios; grants in the pipeline and training report executive summary; The Knight News Challenge; journalism and freedom worldwide; and industry developments.
      - Background Materials for January 2008 JAC Meeting, 2008 January 21-22 (Box 7, Folder 6)
        Knight File Number - 4391
        Includes agenda, attendees list and committee member terms; notes and reactions to special November 2007 meeting at MIT on gaming; committee bios; Journalism grant payouts and working and proposed grants; The Knight News Challenge (memo and charts describing process in 2008; status of last year's winner; spreadsheet on semi-finalists); Knight Commission on the Information Needs of Communities in a Democracy (summary of the commission and director's bio); Community Foundation Initiative (summary, media trends and questionnaire); and Universal Digital Access Grant Write-up.
    - First Amendment, 2019; 7.2
      - Crisis in Democracy Renewing Trust in America, 2019 (Box 1, Folder 5)
        Knight File Number - 5991
        Crisis in Democracy Renewing Trust in America, The Report of the Knight Commission on Trust, Media and Democracy. Published in 2019, copyright The Aspen Institute, Communications and Society Program under Creative Commons License NC 4.0. Supported by a 2017 grant G-2017-54086. 2 copies of printed report.
    - Program Director's Files, 1975-2015; 7.3
      The files include an undated description of the Journalism Program's goals and grant priorities, a record of the program grants made from 1975 to 1992, information about the First Amendment issue (1986, 1991), a report, dated 1986, by Philip Meyer on major journalism grants in the United States, a report on the Knight Science Journalism Fellowships at MIT (1992), journalist education (1993), Knight Foundation's interest in attaining a free press in Eastern Europe (1993), and the Newspaper Association of America Foundation's meeting of newspaper-related foundations (1993, 1994).
      The series includes files kept by Del Brinkman, Journalism Program Director. His files contain notes for a statement on the education of journalists for the 21st century, and journalism education in general. A report, dated 1995, by the Institute for Journalism Excellence, which was funded by Knight Foundation, can also be found in this series.
      - Grants Made in Journalism, 1975-1992 (Box 1, Folder 1)
        Knight File Number - 2233
        Four lists, arranged alphabetically by grantee, of grants made by the Knight Foundation in journalism. The first list covers the years 1975 through March, 1986. There are three additional lists covering grants made during the years 1990, 1991 and 1992.
      - First Amendment Issue, 1986 July 3-November 14 (Box 1, Folder 2)
        Knight File Number - 2234
        Letters and memos to/from Creed Black, Journalism Advisory Committee, discussing Knight Foundation's support of First Amendment projects.
      - Major Journalism Grants in the United States, 1986 July 21 (Box 1, Folder 3)
        Knight File Number - 2235
        Research paper prepard by Philip Meyer, Chapel Hill, NC. Knight Foundation is mentioned.
      - Knight Foundation's Journalism Program, 1991 December 2 (Box 1, Folder 4)
        Knight File Number - 2232
        Two versions of a report, titled "Journalism" which describes the Knight Foundation's program, including grant priorities and goals.
      - First Amendment Issue, 1991 May 30-November 7 (Box 1, Folder 5)
        Knight File Number - 2236
        Discussion of possibility of Knight Foundation funding a coalition of First Amendment groups in California, North Carolina and Florida.
      - Report on Knight Science Journalism Fellowhips at M.I.T., 1992 April 7-June 30 (Box 1, Folder 6)
        Knight File Number - 2237
        Background information on the Knight Science Journalism Fellowship program, a professional development program for mid-career science and technology writers.
      - General Correspondence, 1992 April 1-December 18 (Box 1, Folder 7)
        Knight File Number - 3982
        General correspondence includes invitations to join the Journalism Advisory Committee, and other correspondence to the committee, including Creed Black's memo re: recruiting for a journalism program officer.
      - General Correspondence, 1993 January-September (Box 1, Folder 8)
        Knight File Number - 3984
        General correspondence includes letters to new JAC members, and information on the appointment of Del Brinkman.
      - Educating Journalists for the 21st Century, 1993 April 9-September 1 (Box 1, Folder 9)
        Knight File Number - 2238
        Correspondence relating to the improvement of journalism education, and the establishment of a blue ribbon panel to develop a plan for educating journalists for the 21st century and beyond. Also included is the text of a speech, "Educating our Successors", delivered by Creed Black before the California Newspaper Publishers Association in 1979.
      - Free Press in Eastern Europe, 1993 January 15-March 8 (Box 1, Folder 10)
        Knight File Number - 2295
        Background information, memos, transcripts, and notes re: Knight Foundation-sponsored meeting to develop strategies for supporting a free press in Eastern Europe and the former Soviet Union. Status reports on the state of the press in this area are included.
      - Newspaper Association of America Foundation, 1993 January 21-1994 March 24 (Box 1, Folder 11)
        Knight File Number - 2296
        Meeting materials and correspondence re: series of meeting of newspaper-related foundations. Knight Foundation hosted one of the meetings.
      - General Correspondence, 1994 January 5-August 5 (Box 1, Folder 12)
        Knight File Number - 3983
        General correspondence includes letters to new JAC members, and discussion on the Knight Chairholder at Duke University.
      - Newspaper Association of America Foundation, 1994 June 12 (Box 1, Folder 13)
        Knight File Number - 2297
        Letter from NAA to Creed Black approving the membership of Knight Foundation.
      - Notes Towards a Statement on Educating Journalists for the 21st Century, 1993 December 27-1994 July 22 (Box 1, Folder 14)
        Knight File Number - 1858
        Del Brinkman's correspondence with different publishers (Robert Giles, Detroit News; Wichita Eagle), and with universities (Nebraska, Maryland, Kansas, North Carolina, Arizona State). Much of the correspondence concerns educating journalists for the 21st Century. Also included are memos re: education of journalists, a position paper, "Notes Towards a Statement on Education Journalists for the 21st Century, and several copies of articles and speeches on the subject.
      - General Correspondence, 1995 January-October (Box 2, Folder 1)
        Knight File Number - 3985
        General correspondence includes letters to new JAC members, and information on the dedication of Lee Hills Hall.
      - Journalism Focus Group Meeting, 1995 January 16 (Box 2, Folder 2)
        Knight File Number - 2298
        Notes on the Journalism Focus Group Meeting with Journalism Educators sponsored by Knight Foundation. Five audio cassettes of this session are available.
      - Journalism Focus Group Meeting, 1995 January 17 (Box 2, Folder 3)
        Knight File Number - 2299
        Notes on the Journalism Focus Group Meeting with Journallism Editors sponsored by Knight Foundation.
      - Position Paper on Action Plan for Knight Foundation on Educating Journalists for the 21st Century, 1995 July 3 (Box 2, Folder 4)
        Knight File Number - 2300
        First draft prepared by Del Brinkman
      - Report on the 1995 Institute for Journalism Excellence, 1995 November-December (Box 2, Folder 5-7)
        Knight File Number - 2301
        Report was prepared by Diane Borden, Project Director, at the American Society of Newspaper Editors (ASNE). The Institute, which was funded by the Knight Foundation, was designed to "re-invigorate the ties between journalism educators and journalism practitioners", by having educators work during the summer at host newspapers. 3 folders
      - Project on Public Life and the Press, 1995 August-December (Box 2, Folder 8)
        Knight File Number - 2302
        Proposal and supporting documentation prepared by The National Issues Convention, which brought together 600 voters to deliberate issues with presidential candidates.
      - Public Journalism, 1995 April-June (Box 2, Folder 9)
        Knight File Number - 2303
        Articles on public journalism authored by Jay Rosen, director of the Knight Foundation-funded project on Public Life and the Press.
      - Evaluations of Knight International Press Fellowships, 1994 February 17-1997 December 9 (Box 2, Folder 10)
        Knight File Number - 3986
        Reports on the fellows who participated in programs to assist journalists in third-world countries and evaluations of the programs, with suggestions for improvements in training and follow-up.
      - General Correspondence, 1996 February 6-November 11 (Box 2, Folder 11)
        Knight File Number - 3993
        General correspondence includes invitations to join the Journalism Advisory Committee, and other correspondence to the committee.
      - Journalism Grant Evaluations, 1994 February 17-1996 August 20 (Box 2, Folder 12)
        Knight File Number - 3996
        Details on evaluations of journalism programs undertaken up until 1996.
      - General Correspondence, 1997 February 17 (Box 3, Folder 1)
        Knight File Number - 3994
        General correspondence consists of two invitations to join the JAC.
      - General Correspondence, 1998 January 16-December 2 (Box 3, Folder 2)
        Knight File Number - 3995
        General correspondence includes information on membership of the JAC and the leadership grant initiative.
      - Knight Foundation's Journalism Program Prepares for the 21st Century, 1998 (Box 3, Folder 3-5)
        Knight File Number - 3997
        Report contains information of the 1995 journalism strategic plans and planning, major grants from 1988, and responses to Journalism's request for suggestions on Knight Foundations's goals, priorities and initiatives. Three folders
      - Major Journalism Programs and Projects of KF during the Presidency of Creed Black, 1998 (Box 3, Folder 6)
        Knight File Number - 3998
        Lists the grants and amounts awarded.
      - Overview of the Knight Foundation Journalism Program, 1998 (Box 3, Folder 7)
        Knight File Number - 2304
        Prepared by Del Brinkman in 1998, it provides a summary of the major journalism programs and projects sponsored by Knight Foundation from 1998 through 1997.
      - General Correspondence, 1999 January 11-December 29 (Box 3, Folder 8)
        Knight File Number - 3999
        General correspondence includes information on membership of the JAC and follow-up of JAC meetings.
      - Report to the Board of Trustees by Del Brinkman, 1999 March 16 (Box 3, Folder 9)
        Knight File Number - 4000
        Provides a summary of activities, grants awarded, and strategic planning.
      - 2000+ Planning by Ralph Lowenstein, 1999 June 24 (Box 3, Folder 10)
        Knight File Number - 4001
        Summary and analysis of 52 responses to Del Brinkman's request for thinking on KF's goals and objectives. The summary was prepared by consultant, Ralph Lowenstein.
      - Leadership Grant Initiative, 1999 November 3 (Box 3, Folder 11)
        Knight File Number - 4002
        Memo from Del Brinkman to Penny McPhee outline his proposal to improve the quality of journalism and the way the public is served through journalism excellence by establishing a Leadership Grant initiative.
      - General Correspondence, 2000 January 17-February 16 (Box 3, Folder 12)
        Knight File Number - 3987
        General correspondence includes a letter re: Harvard University's request for The Media and Democracy program and a letter to Tina Hills with recollections of her late husband, Lee.
      - Background Material for Journalism Five-Year Strategic Plan, 2000 August 7 (Box 3, Folder 13)
        Knight File Number - 3989
        Contents include the 1995-2000 strategic plan for journalism; journalism grants made, 1995-2000, vision statement, 1995 strategic plan, draft of a 2000 strategic plan, minutes of several JAC meetings, and a leadership grant memo.
      - General Correspondence, 2001 February 14 (Box 3, Folder 14)
        Knight File Number - 3988
        Letter from the President of the University of Maryland to Hodding Carter re: KF's support of the Knight Center for Specialized Journalism.
      - Journalism Grants as of July 1, 2003, 2003 July (Box 3, Folder 15)
        Knight File Number - 3990
        List of active grants with a summary describing each of them.
      - Diversity Task Force Meeting Materials, 2003 November 14 (Box 3, Folder 16)
        Knight File Number - 4086
        Includes an agenda, participant list and background memo; Prime Movers Project proposal; list of active diversity grants; and a proposal for new concepts about diversity report.
      - Journalism Grants as of April 1, 2004, 2004 April (Box 4, Folder 1)
        Knight File Number - 3991
        List of active grants with a summary describing each of them. Grants are grouped in the following catagories: education and training, press freedom, news and newsroom diversity, electronic and new media, and news in the public interest.
      - Unity Convention, 2004 August (Box 4, Folder 2)
        Knight File Number - 3381
        Memo from Denise Tom, Journalism Initiatives Program Officer, to Eric Newton, Program Director re: Unity Convention which Tom attended in August 2004. Highlights mentioned were the Council of National Journalism Organizations meeting, Media funders, Prime Movers, and the Midcareer program directors meeting. Mentioned were several KF grantees.
      - Anti-MOSAIC Campaign, 2004 May 3-11 (Box 4, Folder 3)
        Knight File Number - 4359
        Copies of emails, correspondence and memos re: campaign of protest against the rebroadcast, in the United States, of a Hezbollah-supported news broadcast. The rebroadcasting was done by Link TV's MOSAIC television show, which rebroadcast a variety of Middle Eastern newscasts. Link TV was supported by grants from KF and the Hewlitt Foundation. A pro-Israeli group mounted a protest campaign against the funders for supporting MOSAIC>
      - Focus on the First, 2004-2007 (Box 4, Folder 4)
        Knight File Number - 4397
        Two items: Memo from Eric Newton re: Future of the First Amendment outline launch and Brochure and calendar for the Channel One Network, a cable tv network seen exclusively in the classroom. The brochure highlights 1Voice, with information about the Knight Foundation's First Amendment study on teens and the first amendment. Includes quotes from Alberto Ibarguen and Eric Newton.
      - Journalism Outcomes Report Update, 2005 November (Box 4, Folder 5)
        Knight File Number - 3992
        The report lists 90 summaries for 2005 grants and ranks their outcomes as to whether they have achieved their goals and provides analysis.
      - Electronic and New Media: Knight Foundation Update, 2003 July-2005 May (Box 4, Folder 6)
        Knight File Number - 4087
        Two items: 1) meeting materials for the electronic and new media task force, include a membership list and research reports; and 2) a revised electronic and new media investment plan, which includes a survey of professionals in the field.
      - Media Funders Meeting, 2006 April 24 (Box 4, Folder 7)
        Knight File Number - 4548
        Hosted by The Bill & Melinda Gates Foundation and KF. Handout consists of a directory of donor participants and Knight International Press Fellows.
      - Knight Center for Specialized Journalism, University of Maryland, 2006, 2006 January 13-August 21 (Box 4, Folder 8)
        Knight File Number - 4549
        Participant materials for the first annual meeting of the Knight Center's new national advisory board. Eric Newton attended. Included is an evaluation report and supplement prepared by Lee Becker and Tudor Vlad re: Knight Fellowship Program at the Knight Center for Socialized Journalism.
      - Journalism Grants to University of Maryland, 2007 (Box 4, Folder 9)
        Knight File Number - 4550
        Includes a summary of grants, 1984-2007 and grant write-ups from 1997-2007.
      - Knight News Challenge, 2007-2011 June (Box 4, Folder 10)
        Knight File Number - 5247
        Two versions of a review, Knight News Challenge: Assessing the Early Winners, 2007 - 2008, which was prepared by LFA Group for KF in June 2011. The report includes winner profiles and lessons learned. Also included are other KNC information re: Top proposals and recommended finalists, 2007; Marketing Guide, 2008; Report on 2008 Challenge for Alberto Ibarguen; Year 3 Final Review instructions and finalists, 2009; and Notes for improving the KNC website, no date.
      - Meeting of the Carnegie-Knight Initiative on the Future of Journalism Education, 2011 June 15-16 (Box 4, Folder 11)
        Knight File Number - 4867
        Background materials for the meeting which explored the future of curriculum reform at Carnegie-Knight journalism schools. Also included were discussions of the News21 internship program and a knowledge-based journalism book project.
      - Memos and Emails, 2006-2015 May 6 (Box 4, Folder 12)
        Knight File Number - 5600
        Memos and emails re: Gates Foundation; Journalism Grantmaking; Cornell University's Writing Seminar Program; Media Development Loan Fund; KF staff performance plan; KF blog ideas; news sources; and an invitation to a webinar on Growing a Nonprofit News Site jointly hosted by KF and the Poynter Institute.
    - Programs - International Press Fellowship Program, 1991-2007; 7.4